Guide to the Michael Polanyi Papers 1900-1975
University of Chicago Library
Polanyi, Michael. Papers
1900-1975
30 linear feet (60 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Michael Polanyi, chemist and philosopher, was born, Budapest, Hungary, 1891. He received his M.D. (1913) and Ph.D (1917) from the University of Budapest. He worked at Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Fibre Chemistry, Berlin, 1920 to 1923, and the Institute of Physical and Electro-Chemistry, Berlin, 1923 to 1933. He was chair of physical chemistry, 1933 to 1948, and professor of social studies, 1948-58, at the University of Manchester. Polanyi was senior research fellow, Merton College, Oxford, from 1958 to 1976. Died, 1976. The papers of Michael Polanyi contains personal and professional correspondence; research notes; manuscripts of lectures, published and unpublished works, speeches, German scientific writings, patents, and poetry; diaries and notebooks; offprints; and memorabilia, including photographs, clippings, a sound recording of an interview with Polanyi, Christmas cards, and invitations. Also includes photocopies of title pages of the 1,500 books from Polanyi's library. Correspondents include Joseph Oldham, Marjorie Grene, Harry Prosch, Arthur Koestler, Karl Mannheim, Edward Shils, and Eugene Wigner. Manuscripts and correspondence reveal the range of Polanyi's philosophical thought and interests in intellectual liberty and the issue of planning in science. Correspondence also illustrates Polanyi's participation in the organization of the Congress for Cultural Freedom and the Committee on Science and Freedom.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open to research.
Biographical Note
Michael Polanyi was born in Budapest in 1891, and though his career as a scientist and philosopher led him far from his native Hungary, the intellectual milieu of his childhood remained a life-long influence on his work. His father was an engineer and businessman and his Russian mother, Cecile, wrote a fashion column for the German-language newspaper in Budapest. Throughout the early years of Polanyi's childhood, the family was financially successful, but most of their resources were lost before the first World War, leaving the children largely dependent on Polanyi's brother Karl for support. Despite this poor financial situation, Cecile Polanyi maintained a salon for Hungarian literary figures.
Polanyi grew up in a literate, political world. With his brother Karl and friend Oscar Jászi, a young Polanyi helped to found the Galilei Circle, a Hungarian nationalist group which promoted Hungarian cultural traditions and worked for an independent Hungarian state. Polanyi became a Doctor of Medicine at Budapest University in 1913 and served as a medical officer in the Austro-Hungarian army during World War I. His earliest scientific paper, "Chemistry of Hydrocephalic Liquid," was published at age 19. Throughout the war, he worked on the application of quantum theory to the third law of thermodynamics and on the thermodynamics of adsorption. In 1916, he published his work on adsorption, one of the first of over two hundred scientific papers he was to publish before his move into philosophy in 1948. His theory of adsorption was accepted by the chemistry faculty of Budapest University which awarded him a Ph.D. in 1917.
Following the war, in the autumn of 1920, Polanyi received an appointment to the new Institute of Fibre Chemistry in Berlin, part of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute. His early years in Berlin are recounted in the 1962 essay, My Time with X-Rays and Crystals. Fritz Haber, the Director of the prestigious Institute of Physical Chemistry, sent Polanyi off to expand his laboratory skills in order to achieve full acceptance by the German scientific community. He succeeded in this with a study of x-ray diffraction of cellulose fibers, and in 1923 he was appointed to the Institute of Physical Chemistry to work under Haber. During the following ten years in Berlin, Polanyi established himself as one of Germany's leading physical chemists. He worked with some of the most prominent scientists of the age, including Eugene Wigner with whom he was to share a life-long friendship.
For Polanyi, who was a Jew, the coming to power of Hitler and the National Socialist Party marked the end of his career in Germany. In 1933, prompted by repeated attacks on Jewish intellectuals, Polanyi accepted a chair in physical chemistry created for him at the University of Manchester. He continued with the chemical studies begun in Berlin, and his laboratory at Manchester attracted students and established scientists from all over the world. His contacts with non-refugee German scientists decreased, but from 1933 to 1948 (the year Polanyi accepted the chair of Social Studies at Manchester), his contacts with British scientists increased, and eventually included William H. Bragg and his son William L. Bragg, Arthur Allmand, Patrick Blackett, Christopher Ingold, Cyril Hinshelwood, and Eric Rideal. There are a number of exchanges from this period with Max Born and Erwin Schrödinger, but perhaps his most important associate during this period was Japanese chemist Juro Horiuchi.
During these first years in England, Polanyi turned his interest to the philosophical attack presented free societies by the totalitarian governments of Germany and Russia. In 1935, he published his first non-scientific work, "U.S.S.R. Economics—Fundamental Data System and Spirit." This was accompanied by a film which criticized the system of Soviet economics as an attack on liberty. While devoting most of his time to scientific pursuits, Polanyi spent part of the next five years in work on The Contempt of Freedom (1940), his large-scale critique of totalitarian government. In the early 1930s, Polanyi had visited the Soviet Union and had become friends with two Soviet chemists, Alexander Frumkin and Nicolai Semenoff. Both were to write him asking that he stop his attacks on Soviet economic policies.
A devoted Keynesian, Polanyi's writings on economic subjects are divided between attacks on the Soviet system and lucid commentaries on the work of Lord Keynes. Between 1935 and c1950, Polanyi corresponded with a number of important economists including Friedrich A. Hayek, David Caradog Jones, Wolfe Mays, and John Maynard Keynes. His position as a scientist and a social thinker led him to become involved with a group of intellectuals in England concerned with social problems. This group, the Moot, was convened by Joseph H. Oldham, editor of the Christian Newsletter.
The war was passed in divided intellectual pursuits. Polanyi continued his scientific studies and tried to obtain military projects through Sir William Lawrence Bragg. At the same time he wrote on economic subjects. It was during these years that he helped to found, with John R. Baker, the Society for Freedom in Science which he used as a forum for developing his ideas on scientific liberty.
The philosophic ideas of Michael Polanyi first took characteristic shape during the war years. His opposition of planning in science led to an epistemology of science grounded in a belief in an individual nature of discovery, unhindered by official or dogmatic interference. In 1945, Polanyi published Science, Faith and Society, his first large-scale philosophic work and the foundation for his theory of knowledge. The evolution of Polanyi's thought is traceable in the Papers through a number of manuscripts, beginning with his 1936 On Truth, On Reason and Science and Liberty and continuing with his studies of scientific planning throughout the late 1930s and early 1940s. By 1950, the date of the first of his University of Chicago lecture series, The Logic of Liberty, his interest in philosophy dominated all other intellectual concerns.
In 1951, Polanyi was offered a position at the University of Chicago on the Committee on Social Thought and was awarded a large grant by the Rockefeller Foundation. The State Department, however, held up his immigrant visa under the McCarran Act until Polanyi withdrew it, consequently remaining in Manchester. He was suspected of past involvement in a subversive organization, the Galilei Circle of his Hungarian youth. Ironically, he was involved with the most significant intellectual anti-Communist force in post-war Europe, the Congress for Cultural Freedom. When Princeton University made Polanyi an honorary Doctor of Science during its 1949 bicentennial celebration, he was cited as "a veteran campaigner against those who would take from science the freedom she requires for the pursuit of truth." His book, The Logic of Liberty, 1950, would continue his attack on Soviet infringement of personal liberty begun nearly twenty years before.
Following this debacle, Polanyi became a regular visitor to the United States and the University of Chicago. Two of his lecture series here were ultimately published as The Logic of Liberty (1950) and Meaning (1936). Between 1951 and 1958, when he retired from Manchester to accept a position of senior research fellow at Merton College, Oxford, Polanyi wrote his central philosophical work, Personal Knowledge. Personal Knowledge grew out of Polanyi's 1951 Gifford lectures.
Another aspect of Michael Polanyi's life, political involvement, can be traced throughout the collection. Prominence as a scientist and anti-Communist social thinker led Polanyi to recognition as an important commentator on current affairs. Throughout World War II, his letters, articles, and reviews appeared in various British journals, particularly the Manchester Guardian.
Polanyi was a major figure in the debate over intellectual liberty and most particularly the issue of planning in science. He was co-founder with John R. Baker of the Society for Freedom in Science in 1941. In the post-war period, Polanyi was an active participant in the organization of the Congress for Cultural Freedom and its English affiliate, the Committee on Science and Freedom. His close involvement with these organizations is best illustrated in the correspondence through exchanges with such figures as Raymond Aron, Konstantin A. Jelenski, Shepard Stone, and Michael Josselson.
By 1972, age and infirmity had slowed Professor Polanyi's work. His final years were spent at home in Oxford and in a Northampton nursing home. During this period, Polanyi's wife of fifty-six years, Magda Kemeney Polanyi, managed his affairs. She supervised the translation of Personal Knowledge into German and was responsible for decisions concerning the disposition of Professor Polanyi's papers and library. Michael Polanyi died in the hospital at Northampton on February 22, 1976. He was eighty-four.
Scope Note
The papers of Michael Polanyi are a continuing testament to the richness of the philosopher's life. In order to facilitate an understanding of the evolving nature of Michael Polanyi's career, the papers have been divided into four basic series and organized in a largely chronological framework: Correspondence (Boxes 1-20); Notes (Boxes 21-25, folder 7); Manuscripts (25:8-44:11); and Offprints and Memorabilia (45-60).
When received, correspondence, manuscripts, notes, and memorabilia had already been sorted by Professor Polanyi's secretary. The correspondence had been arranged alphabetically in yearly files from 1950 to 1975. Earlier correspondence had been grouped together in no particular order. Professor Polanyi's manuscripts were likewise ordered chronologically and labeled by the title given a particular document at the time of its composition and not necessarily by its final title at the time of publication or delivery as a lecture. The notes were segregated into files arranged alphabetically by author and there were several folders of notes labeled "miscellaneous." Memorabilia was scattered throughout the collection in folders of clippings, photographs, and unorganized announcements, invitations and the like. In addition to these relatively clear groupings, a good deal of overlap occurred with notes and letters scattered among the manuscripts. Letters and clippings from Polanyi's mother Cecile had been separately filed. These items (Boxes 18-20) have been separated but not further organized.
The original organization has been largely retained. Correspondence is interfiled chronologically with separate categories for certain specific people and organizations. The letters and manuscripts relating to Polanyi's involvement with John R. Baker and the Society for Freedom in Science and Joseph H. Oldham and the Moot are separate as are letters to and from his close friends and colleagues Marjorie Grene and Harry Prosch. Most of the family correspondence has been interfiled, but there is a box of letters from his brother Karl Polanyi and Karl's wife Ilona which covers over fifty years of family history. All the sections of correspondence are filed chronologically with undated and fragmentary letters arranged alphabetically at the end of the series. The correspondence contains letters to Polanyi as well as copies of letters he sent out. An index of selected names has been prepared which lists his correspondence with significant figures in twentieth-century history and scholarship.
During the course of World War II, Polanyi lost contact with many friends and family on the continent. Correspondence during the early war years, 1939 and 1940, is filled with pleas for assistance from loved ones trapped in occupied lands (3:14-4:5). Polanyi was instrumental in bringing his brothers Karl and Adolf and his sisters Laura and Irene to England (17:9).
Correspondence with Dr. Oldham and papers presented at meetings of the Moot have been grouped together in this collection (15:3-10). Polanyi corresponded independently with two significant members of the Moot, T. S. Eliot and Karl Mannheim. Their letters will be found in the correspondence.
One of the most significant influences on the development of Polanyi's thought was the correspondence he shared with his friend and colleague, philosopher Marjorie Grene. This material has been grouped together (19:1-9), but it contains only two letters which predate Personal Knowledge.
Manuscripts in the collection are also arranged chronologically by date of composition. Their order has been determined by the dates ascribed to them by Polanyi when they were originally filed. Thus, a revised version of a paper will generally fall under the year of its revision and not the year of its composition. Exceptions to this ordering occur with manuscripts composed at an earlier period and drawn together for a lecture series. Such manuscripts have been filed by the dates of their lectures. Titles and descriptions of manuscripts are taken from the text and have not been matched with any bibliography of Polanyi's published writings. It is hoped that this approach, respecting the integrity of Polanyi's original organization and titles, will help to illuminate the evolving nature of his thought.
The manuscripts series jumps from a solid collection of pre-1952 manuscripts to an equally large group of post-1960 manuscripts. This leaves the researcher with sources for the foundation and later developments of Polanyi's thought, but without sources for the work which culminates in Personal Knowledge.
In spite of this lack of early material relating to Polanyi's philosophical thought, later correspondence with Marjorie Grene and others is abundant. Polanyi's thought ranged over a multitude of ideas and disciplines. His views on the mind led to correspondence with Carl Rogers, Abraham Maslow and Erik Erikson; his views on language, with Noam Chomsky and Yehoshua Bar-Hillel; on visual perception, with Maurice Pirenne. Perhaps the most consistently stimulating exchanges in the collection occur with old friends like Grene, Arthur Koestler, and Eugene Wigner.
The range of Polanyi's thought in his later years was enormous. The Logic of Personal Knowledge, a festschrift presented to Polanyi on his seventieth birthday in 1961, contains essays by such prominent thinkers and friends as Arthur Koestler, Raymond Aron, Bertrand de Jouvenel, and C. V. Wedgwood. After 1960, there are a large number of manuscripts in the collection which help to demonstrate the growth of Polanyi's thought. Of particular interest are the sets of lectures delivered between 1960 and 1971. Included in this group are the 1960 Gunning Lectures, Perceptions of Personal Knowledge (34:1-6); the 1962 Terry Lectures (35:6-12); Man in Thought, a 1964 Duke University lecture series (36:4-37:3); Wesleyan lectures of 1965, Man's Place in the Universe (37:15-38:5); and Meaning, lectures and seminars at the University of Chicago in 1969 (39:6-40:1). The majority of philosophical manuscripts are corrected typescripts of lectures and papers delivered between 1960 and 1972. There are no galley proofs in the collection for any of Polanyi's publications.
Research notes have been divided into two groups: subject and author. The subject notes are drawn together from inter-related material in the folders originally marked "miscellaneous." "Author notes" are an alphabetical arrangement of Polanyi's files of quotations by and comments on a variety of scientific, political, philosophical, and literary figures. The memorabilia in the collection has been separated into the following categories: photographs and postcards; general memorabilia including announcements, addresses, and receipts; clippings, dissertations, and interviews with Polanyi; and offprints and other published materials.
Nearly all of the series of research notes are devoted to philosophy. When received, the notes had been divided between "author notes" and "miscellaneous." The miscellaneous notes have been sorted by subject and inventoried. The author notes have been arranged alphabetically by last name of author. Most of this material contains summaries, commentaries, and quotations relating to the work of a specific author. Together these sets of notes formed a reference file which Polanyi could turn to in writing.
INDEX OF SELECTED CORRESPONDENTS
This index highlights Polanyi's correspondence with a wide range of prominent individuals between 1913 and 1975. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated letters arranged alphabetically at the end of the series. Indexed names are followed by the dates of their correspondence or, if there are undated letters, by the number of pieces followed by n.d. Correspondence of John R. Baker, Joseph H. Oldham, Marjorie Grene, Julius and Elsa Hollo, Harry Prosch, Karl and Ilona Polanyi, and Cecile Polanyi follows the undated group.
Arthur J. Allmand, 1931 July 3. 1932 May 17; June 2, 21; Nov. 29. 1933 Apr. 6; Sept. 8; Dec. 22. 1934 Mar. 22; Apr. 8; Sept. 26; Oct. 2. 1937 Jan. 15; Dec. 28. 1939 May 22, 24. 1941 Mar. 31. 1945 May 13.
Edward N. da Costa Andrade, 1944 Oct. 8, 10.
Raymond Aron, 1961 Mar. 28. 1967 May 9, 31. 1971 June 2. 1972 Sept. 22.
Yehoshua Bar-Hillel 1964 Dec. 15, 30. 1965 Mar. 1. 1966 Mar. 25; Apr. 25.
Paul Beck, 1930 Sept. 4. 1933 June 2; Aug. 4; Oct. 3. 1938 Jan. 15. 1947 Oct. 29. 1948 Jan. 8.
Daniel Bell, 1972 June 1, 15.
Ronald P. Bell, 1947 Dec. 12.
Morroe Berger, 1960 Nov. 15.
Ernst Berl, 1922 Mar. 28; May 2.
Arnold Berliner, 1924 Feb. 7; June 23.
John D. Bernal, 1935 Mar. 26; Apr. 11, 29. 1938 Sept. 10, 13. 1939 Nov. 14. 1946 Jan. 8, 30.
Sir William Beveridge, 1938 Apr. 29. 1939 May 24, 25.
Arthur Binz, 1922 Mar. 7, 8; May 23.
Niels Bjerrum, 1945 Nov. 1; Dec. 27.
Patrick M. Blackett, 1937 July 18. 1938 May 10. 1939 Aug. 26. 1941 Oct. 28; Nov. 3. 1942 Sept. 21, 22. 1944 Nov. 9. 1945 Mar. 9, 13; May 16; June 22, 28; July 27; Aug. 1. 1946 May 10; Dec. 20. 1947 July 11; Sept. 15. 1948 Mar. 16. 1949 May 9.
Max Bodenstein, 1935 June 17. 1937 Sept. 13.
Nils Bohr, 1938 July 8.
Karl F. Bonhoeffer, 1933 July 12. 1938 June 3. 1939 June 16. 1950 Mar. 13.
Max Born, 1921 Jan. 12; June 13; Sept. 26. 1924 July 10. 1936 Feb. 19. 1941 July 29, 31. 1942 Feb. 12, 14, 20; June 30; July 9; Sept. 21, 27; Oct. 5; Nov. 21; Dec. 16.
Sir William Henry Bragg, 1934 June 30; July 2, 6. 1938 Nov. 22. 1939 Jan. 14.
Sir William L. Bragg, 1933 June 30; July 7, 10, 14; Nov. 22. 1942 May 22; Oct. 28; Dec. 14. 1943 Jan. 7; May 22; July 1; Sept. 1, 14, 24, 27. 1946 Jan. 25. 2 n.d.
Georg Bredig, 1913 Feb. 1, 12. 1914 Feb. 16. 1915 Jan. 28; Apr. 25; Dec. 31. 1917 Feb. 12. 1923 June 23. 1924 Feb. 29. 1932 Nov. 18. 1 n.d.
Percy W. Bridgman, 1923 Mar. 24. 1943 Sept. 8. 1946 Dec. 19.
William F. Buckley, 1964 Aug. 4. 1968 Mar. 12, 21; Apr. 11.
Alan Bullock, 1970 Jan. 20, 26.
Hadley Cantril, 1962 July 2. 1964 June 10; July 28; Oct. 26.
Jean-Claude Casanova, 1969 Feb. 13; Mar. 20; June 6; Sept. 26; Oct. 24. 1970 Mar. 10; Nov. 27. 1971 Jan. 22; Apr. 8; June 21, 25.
Noam Chomsky, 1966 Nov. 6.
Jens A. Christiansen, 1932 Nov. 14. 1948 Mar. 1, 10; June 22.
Nevill Coghill, 1963 Oct. 22, 24; 1969 Oct. 22.
John Bell Condliffe, 1940 Sept. 16.
Erika Cremer, 1932 June 17. 1952 July 22.
J. A. Crowther, 1942 Jan. 23.
Lionel Curtis, 1944 Dec. 18, 21. 1945 Jan. 1, 9, 10, 20.
Cyril Darlington, 1962 Aug. 31; Sept. 3.
Frederick G. Donnan, 1932 May 16; Oct. 6. 1933 Jan. 20; Apr. 7, 19. 1941 Dec. 14. 1943 Jan. 29; Sept. 9.
Ludwig Ebert, 1933 July 3.
Paul Ehrenfest, 1932 June 6.
Albert Einstein, 1920 Mar. 1. 1922 Mar. 14. 1932 Oct. 13.
Daniel D. Eley, 1939 Apr. 8; May 9; Dec. 15. 1940 June 6, 11; Oct. 13. 1944 Sept. 7, 30; Oct. 2. 1945 June 4. 1946 Jan. 6. 1947 Jan. 7; Mar. 18. 1974 Jan. 3, 8, 17.
Mircea Eliade, 1969 Jan. 24.
T. S. Eliot, 1944 June 3, 7, 27, 29. 1945 Mar. 5; May 23, 25; Dec. 26.
Pierre Emmanuel, 1967 Oct. 5. 1968 Apr. 9, 25; June 4. 1969 May 2.
Dorothy Emmet, 1947 Sept. 18. 1973 Mar. 27. 5 n.d.
Erik Erikson, 1965 Oct. 28.
Henry Eyring, 1933 Oct. 28. 1934 Nov. 24. 1936 Nov. 6. 1937 Feb. 18; Mar. 23. 1938 Sept. 22. 1951 Mar. 6.
Kasimir Fajans, 1915 May 24; Oct. 3; Dec. 12. 1916 Jan. 13; Mar. 22; May 27; June 28; Oct. 22. 1917 Sept. 2. 1918 Mar. 21; June 26; Oct. 5. 1920 Feb. 3; June 28; Sept. 1; Dec. 31. 1921 Jan. 4; Apr. 4; May 5. 1 n.d.
Herbert Feigl, 1969 Mar. 18, 31.
Laura Fermi, 1966 Oct. 3, 7, 12.
James Franck, 1921 Nov. 17. 1925 July 3. 1927 Apr. 23. 1932 Aug. 30. 1961 May 18.
Herbert Freundlich, 1914 Apr. 12. 1918 Apr. 14. 1934 Mar. 24; Apr. 29. 1938 Oct. 21. 1939 Jan. 14; Feb. 16; Apr. 8; July 3.
Alexander Frumkin, 1929 July 28. 1932 Apr. 14; Nov. 28. 1935 Dec. 14. 1941 Dec. 1. 1942 Oct. 18. 1945 June 22. 18 n.d.
Joseph S. Fruton, 1971 Oct. 7, 11.
Dennis Gabor, 1961 June 23.
Charles C. Gillespie, 1966 June 30; July 26; Nov. 4. 1968 Oct. 29.
David Goldstein, 1969 Feb. 25; Mar. 5, 27; Apr. 14, 18; May 2.
Sir Richard Gregory, 1942 Jan. 29, 30. 1943 Feb. 12; June 15.
Eduard Grüneisen, 1922 June 20.
Fritz Haber, 1923 Apr. 16. 1931 Aug. 5, 6; Dec. 31. 1932 June 27; Dec. 18. 1933 Jan. 23; Apr. 26. 2 n.d.
Otto Hahn, 1933 Sept. 21.
Robert S. Hansen, 1963 Jan. 30; Apr. 15; May 1.
Garrett Hardin, 1963 Feb. 21.
Sir Alister Hardy, 1969 Aug. 29; Oct. 16, 21. 1971 Dec. 9, 14. 1972 Apr. 20.
Romano Harré, 1967 Feb. 2; 1975 Feb. 15.
Sir Roy F. Harrod, 1945 Nov. 21, 28; Dec. 3, 19.
Robert D. Haworth, 1947 June 28, 30.
Sir Walter N. Haworth, 1946 Apr. 22.
Friedrich A. Hayek, 1939 Jan. 28. 1940 Jan. 31; Feb. 4; Apr. 18. 1941 May 1; July 1, 26. 1968 Feb. 2.
Werner Heisenberg, 1934 July 9.
Wilfred Heller, 1933 Sept. 12, 20, 22. 1934 Apr. 12. 1938 Oct. 25. 1939 Jan. 2. 2 n.d.
George C. de Hevesey, 1953 Apr. 29.
Joel Hildebrand, 1937 Feb. 26; Mar. 8.
Sir Cyril Hinshelwood, 1935 June 6, 8, 19, 27. 1937 Feb. 9, 12; Apr. 14, 15; June 4, 5. 1941 Jan. 27; Feb. 1. 1946 Feb. 11, 13. 3 n.d.
Lancelot Hogben, 1939 Nov. 23, 27, 30; Dec. 6, 8, 13.
Thorfin R. Hogness, 1942 Aug. 20; Oct. 27; Nov. 11.
Gerald Holton, 1963 Nov. 6, 12, 26. 1973 Sept. 20. 1974 Jan. 7.